<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached on the day of the publick fast, April the 11th, 1679, at St. Margarets Westminster before the Honourable House of Commons / by William Jane ...</title>
            <author>Jane, William, 1645-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12156529</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12156529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55156</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46650)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 604:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached on the day of the publick fast, April the 11th, 1679, at St. Margarets Westminster before the Honourable House of Commons / by William Jane ...</title>
                  <author>Jane, William, 1645-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.C. for Henry Brome, and Richard Chiswel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Hosea VII, 9 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:55156:1"/>
            <head>Sabbati, 12. die Aprilis, 1679.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>ORDERED,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT the thanks of this Houſe be returned to Mr. <hi>Jane</hi> for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Yeſterday Preached before this Houſe; and that he be deſired to Print his Sermon. And that the Members that ſerve for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities do return the thanks.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILL. GOLDESBROUGH. Cler. Dom. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55156:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached on the Day of the Publick Faſt, <hi>April</hi> the 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1679. AT St. <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter;</hi> BEFORE THE Honourable Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>WILLIAM JANE,</hi> B. D. Canon of Chriſt-Church in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Chaplain to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M. C.</hi> for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> and <hi>Richard Chiſwel,</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:55156:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55156:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SERMON ON HOSEAH vii. 9.</hi> Strangers have devoured his ſtrength and he knoweth it not, yea gray hairs are here and there upon him, yet he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Argument of this Chapter is much of the ſame nature with the foregoing, only with this difference, that in that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet directs his ſpeech againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> in this againſt the Ten Tribes. And becauſe in the end of the former Chapter he had given the Jews ſome hopes of their return from Captivity, he proceeds in this, and thoſe which follow to lay open the ſins, and aggravate the guilt of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55156:3"/>thereby to cut off from them all occaſion of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining againſt God, as if he had adjudged them to too ſevere a doom in not affording them the like promiſe of a Temporal reſtitution.</p>
            <p>He makes a diſtinct diſcovery of the ſins and provocations of all orders and degrees of men amongſt them, not only of the common people but of the Princes and the Rulers, not only of the leſſer and inferior Cities, but (and that prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally) of <hi>Samaria</hi> the great Metropolis of their Nation. And this ſeems to be the deſign of the Prophet in almoſt every Verſe of this Chapter: Firſt, to lay before them the ſad calamitous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition whereto their ſins had brought them: Secondly, their ſenſeleſneſs and ſtupidity which increaſed upon them in proportion to their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and grew the more incurable by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of their recovery.</p>
            <p>Thus we read Verſe 7. <hi>They have devoured their Judges, all their Kings are fallen, there is none among them that calleth unto me.</hi> By which words, as I conjecture, the Prophet endeavours to repreſent to them thoſe Treaſons and Conſpiracies, and horrible Butcheries of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which are more particularly deſcribed, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> xv. and which at laſt determined in the utter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding the poſture of their affairs was ſo diſmal and amazing, though there
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55156:3"/>appeared among them ſuch viſible tokens of the Divine vengeance in ſo many revolutions of their Government, ſo many changes of their Kings, who all ſucceeded one another by Sedition, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery and Murther, yet (which is the more dreadful proſpect of the two) there was no man among them ſo far wrought upon by the ſenſe of the publick calamities as to humble himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, to reform his life, or to implore the Divine aſſiſtance for repairing the breaches, and reſtoring Peace, and ſettlement to a periſhing and diſtracted people. The like argument with ſome variety of expreſſion is again repeated in the words of my Text. In which we find re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to us,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The miſery of <hi>Ephraims</hi> Captivity,<note place="margin">Prov. xviii. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrangers have devoured his ſtrength.</hi> By ſtrength here we may underſtand firſt that which the Wiſe man calls <hi>a Defence, a High-wall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. vii. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and a ſtrong City,</hi> the Wealth, Treaſure and Riches of a people. And how far this had been impaired together with the occaſions of it, we have a very large account from the xiii. to the xvii. of 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> Under <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahaz</hi> the ſon of <hi>Jehu</hi> they were ſo <hi>threſht,</hi> and worn out by the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> that there <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained to</hi> Jehoahaz <hi>of all the people but fifty Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings xiii. 7.</note> 
               <hi>ten Chariots, and ten thouſand Foot.</hi> And though afterwards under <hi>Jeroboam</hi> there began to appear ſome glim ps of ſettlement and reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55156:4"/>yet theſe glorious hopes were ſoon defeated by the Invaſion of <hi>Pul</hi> the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> who forced <hi>Menahem</hi> the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to a compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a thouſand Talents of Silver,<note place="margin">xv. 19.</note> 
               <hi>that ſo his hand might be with him to confirm the Kingdom in his hand.</hi> And in this ſtate they continued waſting and conſuming till the coming of <hi>Salmanaſſer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">xvii. 3.</note> who like an inſatiable gulph devoured and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted all.</p>
            <p>Or, II. By ſtrength here may be underſtood that wherein the true ſafety of a Nation doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, which is the Divine Providence, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. Without this the Fortifications of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the Courage of Souldiers, the multitude of Counſellors, the vaſtneſs of Revenues are of no avail at all to the defence and ſecurity of a people. For when ever God withdraws his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and favour from a Nation, he diſmantles their Fortreſſes,<note place="margin">Iſaiah xix. 3.</note> 
               <hi>mingles a perverſe ſpirit in the midſt of their Counſels, makes the heart of a people to melt, and their ſpirit to fail within them,</hi> he curſes the Treaſures of the wicked, and makes the <hi>increaſe of his houſe to depart and flow away.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job xx. 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>Ephraims</hi> ſtrength in the former accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had been devoured by ſtrange men, ſo in this by ſtrange gods.<note place="margin">2 King. xvii. 12.</note> For <hi>they ſerved Idols of which the Lord had ſaid unto them, ye ſhall not do this thing.</hi> And what more likely courſe could they have taken to cut off all their claim and intereſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55156:4"/>in the Divine favour? <hi>They choſe new gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. v. 8.</note> 
               <hi>then was war in the gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely for the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to whom God had made ſuch clear Revelations of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by ſo many repeated experiments of his love, an earneſt of his aſſiſtance, while they continued ſtedfait in his Covenant; for them I ſay thus in a plain defiance to their known duty, to forſake the Lord who brought them out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and to fly for refuge to the gods of the Nations; what is this but to diſtruſt the veracity of Heaven, and ſcorn the Protection of an Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Arm, to renounce the Covenant which had Eſpouſed them to their Maker, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to proclaim a war with the Sovereign of the world? What in all likelihood can be the conſequence of ſuch a daring heinous provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but what we read, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> xvii. 20. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord rejected all the ſeed of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and afflicted them and delivered them into the hand of Spoilers, until he had caſt them out of his ſight.</hi> This then is the miſery of <hi>Ephraims</hi> Captivity, <hi>ſtrangers have devoured his ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We have the ſymptoms of his approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ruin, <hi>Gray hairs are here and there upon him.</hi> Gray hairs may denote either the intenſion and greatneſs, or elſe the duration of his Calamity. And in either ſignification the meaning of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion will amount to this, that the people of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55156:5"/>
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> had been ſo long kept under a continued ſeries of preſſures and afflictions, that they were in a manner worn out with old Age, ready to give up the Ghoſt, and to pine away in their Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; there appeared upon them the conſtant fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners and manifeſt preſages of ruin and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>And whenever God decrees the final conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a people, they may foreſee it themſelves without the prediction of a Prophet. A general diſſoluteneſs of manners, an impudent boldneſs in the practice of iniquity, a neglect and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all the duties of Religion, the looſing the joints of Government by Treaſons and Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, divided intereſts and Diſſenſions among the people, Confuſions and Diviſions in the Church are as infallible ſymptoms of a dying State, of the diſſolution of a Common-wealth and the funeral of a Kingdom, as if a flaming Sword had hung over it, or a voice from Heaven had revealed its doom. Theſe are the gray hairs of the people in the Text. And how near we our ſelves reſemble them, I leave you to judg by comparing our condition at preſent with that of the Ten Tribes before their carrying into Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</p>
            <p>But III. Which is the worſt ſymptom of all, here is deſcribed the general ſenſeleſneſs of that people, notwithſtanding all the judgments of God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55156:5"/>either paſt or preſent, a deep ſleep that had ſeized them (like <hi>Jonah</hi> in the Tempeſt) none awakening himſelf to cry unto God, or to pour out his ſupplications at the Throne of Grace. <hi>This is his condition, yet he knoweth it not</hi> (that is) he does not conſider the greatneſs of his dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or he does not diſcover himſelf to be ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected with the ſenſe of Gods judgments, ſo as to lament, and bewail, and to tremble at them; he does not reſolve them into their proper princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, nor acknowledg the Author of them, which was the hand of God, nor the Impulſive cauſe which was his own iniquity: or laſtly he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it not, that is, he does not comply with the end and deſign of it. Afflictions have not that errand upon him for which they were ſent, but he ſo behaves himſelf under them, as if he had been wholly ignorant what had been done unto him.</p>
            <p>From the words thus explained, I ſhall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<list>
                  <item>I. The end and deſign of Gods judgments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Nation, which is, that they may know and conſider, that they may be brought to a ſenſe of their ſins, to true Repentance and amendment of their lives.</item>
                  <item>II. The contrary effects which they often have upon a ſecure and a ſinful people, which is to make them the more incorrigible and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55156:6"/>in their ſins. Gods judgments are upon him, <hi>yet he knoweth it not.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. I ſhall diſcover ſome Cauſes of it.</item>
                  <item>IV. The greatneſs of the provocation, <hi>Yet he knoweth it not:</hi> This <hi>Yet</hi> hath an Emphaſis, an accent upon it, and denotes ſins under judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be <hi>exceeding ſinful.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. And laſtly, I ſhall conclude with ſome brief Application to our ſelves. I begin with the firſt of theſe which is the end and deſign of Gods judgments upon a Nation, which is that they may know, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And this will appear, 1. From the intention of God in the threatning and inflicting of his judgments. 2. From the natural tendency of the judgments themſelves. God not only threatens but ſends his judgments upon a people on the ſame errand as the Antient <hi>Romans</hi> did their Heralds, before they actually entered upon a war, not peremptorily to declare our doom but to warn us to prevent it by coming in and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to terms of Peace and Reconcilement. <hi>At what inſtant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. xviii. 7, 3.</note> ſays God by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Nation and concerning a Kingdom, to pluck up and to pull down and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it, if that Nation againſt whom I have pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, turn from the evil, I will repent of the evil which I thought to do unto them.</hi> In the xxvi. of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> God in a Prophetical Scheme repreſents the ſoreſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55156:6"/>judgments which were to fall upon his people in ſucceeding Generations, he lays before their eyes the Sword, Peſtilence and Famine, expulſion from the Lords Land into a Land of Enemies and Idols, the ceaſing of the Sacrifices and the ſolemn Feſtivals, and even all the utmoſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of Captivity and Deſolation; and yet in the concluſion of that black Catalogue, which ſeems rather an inventory of what evils the hand of God was able to inflict, than what a people ſhould ſuffer, we have room for Repentance and a reſerve of mercy, Verſe 41. <hi>If then their Uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed hearts be humbled and they then accept the puniſhment of their iniquity, then will I remember my Covenant with</hi> Jacob, <hi>and alſo my Covenant with</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and alſo my Covenant with</hi> Abraham <hi>will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and I will remember the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read in <hi>Joel</hi> ii. of a day of darkneſs and gloomineſs, <hi>ſuch as had never been the like before,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joel ii. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>wither ſhould there be any after it;</hi> ſuch Armies and terrors, <hi>as ſhould make the earth quake, the Heavens tremble, the Sun and Moon to grow dark, and the Stars to withdraw their ſhining.</hi> And yet amidſt all this diſtreſs and perplexity the Lord calls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his people to return unto him, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation likewiſe given that <hi>he will return and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> and leave a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſsing behind him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods wrath was never ſo fiercely kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a perſon or a people, but if true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55156:7"/>intervened, it has removed his hand or at leaſt abated the fierceneſs of the blow. Nay the outward and formal humiliation of an <hi>Ahab</hi> has procured a reprieve,<note place="margin">1 Kings xxi. 29.</note> and ſuſpended the execution. It cannot be denyed but that God ſometimes pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes a people in vengeance without any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or allay of mercy, when he makes a full end of them, and the conſumption overflows in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as in the Caſe of the Ten Tribes under <hi>Salmanaſſer,</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church at the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when the Kingdom of God was taken from them,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. ii. 16.</note> 
               <hi>and wrath came upon them to the uttermoſt;</hi> of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> who have had their Candleſtick removed, and been ſwallowed up by the Inundation of <hi>Mahumetaniſm;</hi> of the famous Churches of <hi>Africa,</hi> which once gave light to the whole Chriſtian world, now overſpred with ignorance and Barbariſm, with a thick <hi>darkneſs that may be felt.</hi> But in all theſe Caſes God never proceeds to exciſion and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off, till all his other corrections have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved uſeleſs and ineffectual, till their iniquities are full, till they are ripe for vengeance, till they have neglected all the ſeaſons of Grace, and out-ſinned the day of their viſitation. Then indeed God grows weary of repenting being preſt with <hi>ſin as a Cart full of ſheaves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the account which the Scripture gives us of the people of <hi>Judah</hi> when they were carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55156:7"/>into Captivity,<note place="margin">2 Chron. xxxvi. 16, 17.</note> they <hi>mocked the meſſengers of God, deſpiſed his word, and miſuſed his Prophets until the wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt his people, till there was no remedy, therefore he brought upon them the King of the</hi> Chaldces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is a Courſe which God then only takes when all other remedies fail. But till then he has mercy in ſtore for a ſinful people even in the midſt of all his ſevereſt diſpenſations. God ſhoots out his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows againſt a Land as <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſhot to <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. xx, 21.</note> with Letters bound about them, not to deſtroy but to inſtruct. As <hi>Gideon</hi> when he vext the men of <hi>Succoth,</hi> is ſaid to <hi>teach</hi> them (or to make them to know) though <hi>with the briers and thorns of the wilderneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. viii. 16. Mic. vi. 9.</note> Gods <hi>Rod</hi> has a <hi>voice</hi> as well as a <hi>ſmart,</hi> and if we <hi>hear</hi> the one we may eſcape the other.</p>
            <p>And upon theſe grounds we may aſſure our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that in this day of the Lords anger, of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and rebuke, which now lies upon this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Land of our Nativity, the Lord has not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over all concern for our peace and ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He waits that he may be gracious and ſtands ready to recal his judgments, as ſoon as we ſhall be contented to be ſaved, to accept of a deliverance. The Lord looks down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this day to take notice of our behaviour under his afflicting hand, how far we are advanced in the practice of Repentance which this day he ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55156:8"/>loudly calls for. There is not a penitent tear, not a devout ſigh, not a mourner in ſecret for them who have no compaſſion on themſelves, nay not a perſon ſwearing and revelling, eating fleſh and drinking wine in this <hi>day when the Lord calls us to weeping, faſting and mourning,</hi> but the Lord obſerves it, and lays it to the account of this Nation as well on the one ſide for the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his mercy, as on the other for the provocation of the fierceneſs of his anger.</p>
            <p>Tis not our utter ruin, that the Lord aims at. For <hi>what profit is there in our blood?</hi> He hath ſet his judgments, as he once did his Prophet, over Kingdoms and over Nations, not barely <hi>to root out,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. i. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and deſtroy, but to build and to plant,</hi> and theſe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial proceedings of his are directed to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not primarily to deſtruction. They are what the Cenſures of the Church ought to be, ſevere in the execution, but ſalutary in the event,<note place="margin">1 Cor. v. 5.</note> delivering up the offender to the <hi>puniſhment of the fleſh,</hi> that ſo by Repentance and amendment thereupon probably enſuing <hi>the ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job xxxiii. 29.</note> Lo all theſe things <hi>worketh God oftentimes with man to bring back his ſoul from the pit, to be enlightened with the light of the living.</hi> And God often viſits iniquity with Rods, when he will not utterly take away his loving kindneſs from a people.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55156:8"/>
            <p>But, II. This will further and more diſtinctly appear from the natural tendency of Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments themſelves. Which will plainly appear in theſe following particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then they have a natural tendency to work in men a ſenſe and acknowledgment of their ſins. Proſperity is apt to adminiſter ſuch abundant va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of freſh delights and ſatisfactions to the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that the ſoul is never at leiſure to retire into it ſelf and take a true eſtimate of its own Eſtate and Conſtitution. The world will never be wanting to preſent the man with baits and allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and external objects to employ his thoughts and gratifie his deſires. And ſo by that means he is enabled for a time to ſuppreſs the voice of Conſcience, and drown the cries of a wounded Spirit. As the <hi>Jews</hi> when they ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed their children to <hi>Moloch,</hi> had their loud In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Muſick, leſt they ſhould perchance hear the out-cries of their periſhing Infants, which might force their obdurate hearts into tender and compaſſionate reſentments.</p>
            <p>But when the hand of God over-reaches him, and affliction ſits cloſe upon him, this embitters his delights, damps his jollity, diſſolves the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Fabric of his imaginary enjoyments, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders all his moſt exquiſite pleaſures toothleſs and inſipid. None of theſe things can then ſtand by him to reſcue him from his miſeries, or give any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55156:9"/>ſweetning to the bitterneſs of his Cup. And thus when God hedges up his way with thorns, and ſtops him in the purſuit of his brutiſh and ſenſual ſatisfactions, then there lies a neceſſity upon him to deſcend into himſelf, when he cannot look abroad, to turn his eyes inward, to take an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act view of his own heart, and diſcover the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his iniquity:<note place="margin">Job xxxvi. 8, 9.</note> When he is once <hi>bound in fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and holden in the Cords of affliction, then will he ſee his work, and his trangreſſions that they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded.</hi> For the mind of man is active, and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, it will always be employed one way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And when it has no outward objects to exerciſe, or divert it, then ſelf-reflexion takes place, and the voice of Conſcience will be heard.</p>
            <p>How ſtupid and ſenſeleſs was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> before Gods judgments fell upon him! He has no ſenſe at all of God or a Providence, of ſin or the wages of it.<note place="margin">Exod. v. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Who is the Lord that I ſhould obey his voice? I know not the Lord, neither will I let</hi> Iſrael <hi>go.</hi> But when the Lord ſent thunder and hail, <hi>and the fire ran along upon the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ix. 23.</note> his ſtomach comes down, his proud heart is a little humbled, the voice of God in the thunder is more effectual, than by his Prophet. For then <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſent and called for <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> and ſaid unto them, <hi>I have ſinned this time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">xxvii. 28.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord is righteous, and I and my people are wicked.</hi> Now therefore <hi>intreat
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55156:9"/>the Lord, that there be no more mighty thanderings and hail, and I will let you go, and ye ſhall ſtay no longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> ſees the hand-writing upon the wall, <hi>his countenance is changed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. v. 6.</note> 
               <hi>his thoughts trouble him, the joynts of his Loins are looſed, and his Knees ſmite one againſt another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> be never ſo puiſſant in defying the threats, and the Omnipotence of God, yet that ſad calamity of eating graſs with the beaſts of the field will bring him upon his knees, and force him to acknowledg, <hi>that the inhabitants of the world are reputed as nothing in compariſon of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">iv. 35.</note> 
               <hi>and that as he doth according to his will in the Armies of Heaven and among the inhabitants of the earth, ſo none can ſtay his hand, or ſay unto him, what doeſt thou?</hi> The wound of Conſcience is not perceived at firſt any more than a wound in the body, as long as the man continues in the ſame briskneſs of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which he was in, when he firſt received it. But when the judgments of God ſtop him in his career, force him to ſit down and reſt himſelf a little, he then begins to cool, and conſider, to feel his wound, and recover the unwelcome ſenſe of the extremity of his pain.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The judgments of God are in their own nature apt to take us off from Carnal confidence and ſecurity, and to fix us in a cloſer dependence upon God. When mens <hi>houſes are ſafe from fear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jo2 xxi. 9.</note> 
               <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55156:10"/>is the rod of God upon them,</hi> they are apt to ſay to the Almighty <hi>Depart from us,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> to center in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and aſcribe their proſperity to their own conduct and contrivance.<note place="margin">Hab. i. 16.</note> When <hi>their portion is fat, and their meat plenteous, then they ſacrifice to their own net, and burn incenſe to their drag.</hi> It is a great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in a manner rooted in the nature of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, to affect an abſoluteneſs and ſufficiency in themſelves, and an independence upon any ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Cauſe. They think it too great a diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them, an upbraiding of their weakneſs (as if they were unable to help themſelves) to be a burden to Providence, and live in a precarious dependence upon him that made them. And therefore ſo long as ſuccor and relief can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from Power or Policy, from Horſes or Horſemen, from any thing within them or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, from Foreign Intereſts, Domeſtic Treaſures, or even Idolatrous compliances, they will keep their diſtance, ſtand at defiance with the Almighty, and never think of placing their truſt upon the <hi>hope of</hi> Iſrael, upon him who is <hi>the confidence of all the ends of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. xiv. 8. Pſal. lxv. 5.</note> 
               <hi>and of them that remain in the broad ſea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was ſenſible enough, that the Law of God would not countenance his uſurpation, and thereupon ſets himſelf to contrive how he might live without him, and ſtand in no need of the influence of his Providence. He makes two
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55156:10"/>Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and then grows con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident and ſecure, that the <hi>work of his hands</hi> would Eſtabliſh him in his Throne. And therefore God Almighty often finds it neceſſary to fruſtrate the Counſels, blaſt the deſigns, and curſe the Policies and attempts of all ſuch as uſurp upon his Prerogative, and aſpire to an abſolute So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty of their own.<note place="margin">Exod. xiv. 25.</note> He takes off <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Chariot-wheels, puts a hook into the noſe of <hi>Sennacherib,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. xix. 28.</note> cruſhes the impious Politician upon the very brink of his deſigns,<note place="margin">Job v. 12.</note> 
               <hi>diſappoints the devices of the crafty, ſo that their hands cannot perform their enterprize.</hi> This is <hi>dignus vindice nodus,</hi> he is as it were concerned in point of honor to vindicate his Authority and government, to make them know that they are but men, and <hi>that the moſt high ruleth over all.</hi> He cuts off all their Proviſions at home, and ſtops all ſuccors from abroad, diſtreſſes them on every ſide, that ſo he may convince them of the vanity and madneſs of their preſumption, that he is a refuge when all elſe fails, and that there is no Sanctuary but in his protection. We read in the xxxiii.<note place="margin">Ezekiel xxxiii.</note> of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> of a very ſevere threatning of miſery and deſolation, Verſe 28. <hi>I will lay the Land moſt deſolate, and the pomp of her ſtrength ſhall ceaſe,</hi> &amp;c. And the reſult and iſſue of this ſeverity is mentioned, Verſe 29. <hi>Then ſhall they know that I am the Lord.</hi> The ſame is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for the end and reaſon of Gods judgments
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55156:11"/>in ſeveral other places of this Prophecy, <hi>that they may know that I am the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">vii. 27. xxiv. 24. xxx. 8.</note> As if it were ſuch a difficult matter for a people to know, and to truſt in God, till all other ſupport were taken from them, till they had nothing left to lean up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their own.</p>
            <p>When Ephraim <hi>ſaw his ſickneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. v. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and Judah his wound, then went</hi> Ephraim <hi>to the</hi> Aſſyrian, <hi>and ſent to King</hi> Jareb, <hi>Menahem</hi> makes a Confederacy with <hi>Pul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings xv. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſea</hi> gives preſents to <hi>Shalmaneſer,</hi> and <hi>Ahaz</hi> ſends an Embaſſy to <hi>Tiglath-pileſer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">xvii. 3.2 Chronicl. xxviii. 20.</note> and ſacrifices to the gods of <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> But alas while they endeavored to avoid the ſmoak they fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire. Theſe were ſo far from <hi>curing of their wound</hi> that they both made it deeper, and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſmart of it. And the gods which <hi>Ahaz</hi> went unto for ſuccor, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> proved <hi>the ruin of him and of all</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>But when God takes the matter into his own hands, becomes a <hi>Lion both to</hi> Ephraim <hi>and</hi> Judah, blocks up all their paſſages, leaves no way open to <hi>Aegypt</hi> or <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> to Idols or Confederates, they then begin to think of returning unto God. <hi>In their affliction they will ſeek me early.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. v. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. The Judgments of God upon a Nation conduce very much to take us off from too great an over-valuing of the Honors, Riches, and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this world. Though ordinarily in our ſober judgments we ſet a greater value upon the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55156:11"/>everlaſting concerns of another world, than up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the ſplendid gayeties, and delights of this, yet they lie under this great diſadvantage, that they are future and at a diſtance, and by that means unable to make ſo deep an impreſſion upon the mind as theſe temporal enjoyments, which are preſent and continually in our eye. And this makes moſt men ſo very fond of the world, ſo eagerly deſirous of building Tabernacles here, and ſtrangely indiſpoſed to ſeek a <hi>better Country,</hi> to reach after <hi>their everlaſting hope,</hi> and the <hi>price of their high calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when God Almighty in the courſe of his Providence ſends his judgments and calamities upon a people, deveſts them of their poſſeſſions, degrades them from their honors, puts a fatal period to their choiceſt pleaſures; How effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally muſt this needs convince us of the tranſitory and periſhable nature of all creature enjoyments, and ſtrip them of thoſe deceitful diſguiſes, under which a deluded fancy is ſo apt to repreſent them!</p>
            <p>When <hi>Baruch</hi> was ſent upon a meſſage, which he fore-ſaw was likely to abridg him of ſome of his former ſatisfactions, he grows melancholy and diſconſolate at the news, and cries out, <hi>Wo is me, for the Lord hath added grief unto my ſorrow, I fainted in my ſighing and find no reſt.</hi> But <hi>thus ſhalt thou ſay unto him</hi> (ſaith God by the Prophet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55156:12"/>
               <hi>Jeremy</hi>) <hi>the Lord ſaith thus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. xlv. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Behold that which I have built will I break down, and that which I have planted will I pluck up, even this whole land, and ſeekeſt thou great things for thy ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeek them not.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, Wouldſt thou live at eaſe in <hi>Sion,</hi> when <hi>Sion</hi> is to be Plowed like a field, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to become a deſolation? Wouldſt thou ſwim in affluence, and enjoy thy pleaſures in a Land now ready to be overſpread with Plagues and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance? Wouldſt thou build thee a ſtately Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace over the blood and bones of thy ſlaughtered brethren? What preferment canſt thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to thy ſelf in the ruines of thy Country? Wouldſt thou make a purchaſe when the world is at an end?</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ludicra ergò publica Trever petis?</hi>
            </q>
            <p>It was <hi>Salvians</hi> expoſtulation with the Citizens of <hi>Treves,</hi> when immediately after the ſacking of their City, they petitioned their Magiſtrates that the Stage-Plays might be reſtored. In like manner does <hi>Jeremy</hi> here control <hi>Baruch</hi> for his now unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable deſires. And may not the ſame ſerve as a check to thoſe amongſt us, who in ſuch times as theſe are ſcraping up all that they can lay hands on, making all the ſordid advantages of the world that they can, as tenants do of an Eſtate, when their Leaſe is expiring. <hi>Soul, take thine eaſe</hi> (ſaid the rich fool in the Goſpel) <hi>thou haſt goods laid up for many years, eat, drink and be merry.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:55156:12"/>But ſurely he had quite other apprehenſions, when he heard that diſmal and ſurprizing voice, <hi>Thou fool, this night ſhall thy ſoul be required of thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. The judgments of God upon a people are apt to unite their hearts in Love and Charity to one another. When men <hi>are at eaſe in</hi> Sion,<note place="margin">Amos vi. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and truſt in the mountains of</hi> Samaria, When <hi>they lie upon beds of Ivory, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and ſtretch themſelves upon their Couches, and eat the Lambs out of the Flock, and the Calves out of the midſt of the Stall;</hi> When <hi>they chant to the Viol,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> live merry, and are full, as they are deſcribed, <hi>Amos</hi> vi. It immediately follows, that then <hi>they are not grieved for the afflictions of</hi> Joſeph. But when we begin to have a ſenſe and feeling of Gods judgments upon our ſelves, this muſt needs (one would think) forcibly engage us to Charity and Compaſſion to our Brethren. We ſhall be ſure to <hi>remember thoſe that are in bonds,</hi> when we our ſelves <hi>are bound with them,</hi> and to help thoſe that are in adverſity, when we find that we alſo are <hi>but fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which haſtned, and precipitated the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and made their final ruin, the more dreadful when it came, was the facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and animoſities which at that time broke forth among them, which engaged them in ſuch incredible ſlaughters and murders of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they never put themſelves into a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of reſiſting the <hi>Romans,</hi> but when they ſaw
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55156:13"/>them approaching their Walls. Which they did <hi>then,</hi> leſt their enemies ſhould come and take the work out of their hands, and ſo deprive them of being the ſole Authors of their own deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>And this I think to be the ſaddeſt ſymptom of approaching vengeance, which is this day viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon this ſinful Nation.</p>
            <p>The modern <hi>Romans</hi> can hardly in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility ever enter in upon us, but at that door, which we our ſelves ſet open by our wide brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and diviſions. And O that we could all be effectually perſuaded in this our day, to know the things that belong unto peace before they be hid from our eyes, to lay aſide all names of parties and diſtinctions, and mind the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, which now lies at ſtake, and which I am ſure ought to be dearer to us, than all other concernments what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
            <p>It was once the fate of two Reverend Martyrs for the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion in the time of their proſperity to be uncharitably diſunited, and alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to a greater height in their affections, than in their judgments. But when the fiery trial in <hi>Queen Maries</hi> days (which for the time it laſted, raged more terribly than any of the Heathen Perſecutions, except that of <hi>Diocleſian</hi>) had ſo deſperately threatned the Common Faith, they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55156:13"/>mutually condeſcended, quitted their animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and both laid down their lives for their undaunted profeſſion of the Faith of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And ſurely this would be one happy effect of the judgments of God upon this Nation, if the fears, which we lie under from our enemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, would engage us to joyn as one man for the compoſing our differences, and diſſenſions at home. And unleſs this be done we have great reaſon to fear, that God will be ſo far provoked by our diviſions, as to give us up to be united in common ſufferings, who would not be perſuaded upon any other terms to be reconciled to one another.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider how the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> triumph in our quarrels, and how active and induſtrious they are in fomenting our differences, and adding fuel to our flames. When the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was divided by the revolt of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> then was the time for <hi>Shiſhak</hi> the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> to forrage the Land,<note place="margin">2 Chronicl. xii. 9.</note> and <hi>take away the treaſures of the Temple of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And O that God would give us all hearts to conſider this, to be ſenſible of our own intereſt, and true to it, that ſo we may no longer expoſe our ſelves and our Country, our lives and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and the beſt Religion in the world, to the advantages of <hi>blood-thirſty, and deceitful men,</hi> who have at this day conſpired againſt us, <hi>to take
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55156:14"/>away both our place and Nation.</hi> And aſſure your ſelves (for he who is truth it ſelf hath ſpoken it) <hi>that a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand, but is brought to deſolation.</hi> And while <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſtands <hi>divided againſt</hi> Manaſſeh, <hi>and</hi> Manaſſeh <hi>againſt</hi> Ephraim; <hi>and every one eats the fleſh of his own arm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. ix. 12.19, 20, 21.</note> and that, at a time <hi>when the</hi> Syrian <hi>is before and the</hi> Philiſtim <hi>behind, and both ready to devour</hi> Iſrael <hi>with open mouth,</hi> we have good reaſon to conclude that <hi>through the wrath of the Lord the Land is darkned,</hi> and infatuated, that <hi>gods anger is not yet turned away, but that his hand is ſtretched out ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of thoſe ends for which Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God ſends his judgments upon a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I proceed in the next place to ſhew</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The contrary effects which they often have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſecure and a ſinful people, which is to make them the more incorrigible, and obſtinate in their ſins. And here we meet with ſome who grow worſe under the rod, though they feel the ſmart of it, yet they will not hear the voice, and as they have heretofore turned Gods Grace, ſo they will now turn his Judgments <hi>into wantonneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a dreadful ſight in the City of <hi>Lyons</hi> when they were ſo infeſted with the Peſtilence, <hi>ut tota civitas buſtum,</hi> that the whole City ſeemed to be but one Grave, the Souldiers in the Garriſon dayly iſſued forth, and committed all ſorts of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55156:14"/>uncleanneſs with the dying and the dead. The like ſtupidity we find in <hi>Salvian</hi> charged upon the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> who were wholly ſet upon their luxury and intemperance in the midſt of their Cities ruines, and among ſo many deaths, which they daily beheld in the ſlaughter of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Citizens had no apprehenſions of their own.</p>
            <p>However they ſaw Gods hand lifted up to ſtrike, it had no effectual influence upon them <hi>to turn to him that ſmote them,</hi> unleſs it were, by the encreaſe of their provocations, as far as was poſſible, to ſmite again. Like thoſe whom we read of, <hi>Revel.</hi> xvi. 11. that <hi>blaſphemed the God of Heaven becauſe of their pains,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Aſsiduitas cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum augmentum Criminum.</hi> A certain argument of the deſperate condition of a people, and that they have already begun their <hi>hell,</hi> where at the ſame time men ſuffer, and blaſpheme their God.</p>
            <p>And this was the ſtate, and conſtitution of the Chriſtian world, at that time when the <hi>Vandals, Goths,</hi> and <hi>Hums,</hi> and other <hi>Barbarians</hi> overran it. So notorious were the Characters of Divine vengeance in the ſuddenneſs of their coming, the number of their Armies, and the invincible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their ſtrength, that we are forced to leave off all enquiry into ſecond cauſes and human deſigns, and conclude them to be nothing elſe,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55156:15"/>but (what one of them called himſelf) the <hi>ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> in the hand of God to puniſh a licentious and a back ſliding people. And yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, they dayly increaſed in their old ſins of Uncleanneſs, and Adultery, Atheiſm, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs, as <hi>Salvian</hi> has left upon Record, who is not half ſo Tragical in the deſcription of the greatneſs of their Calamities, as of the iniquities that ſurvived them.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not proceed any further to ſeek in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this, which is ſo viſible in the carriage of Gods own people. Their whole ſtory is one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Argument to confirm it. They ſinned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſuffering, and ſinned after they were freed from it. The uſe, which they made of their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was to grow more obſtinate in the ſins that cauſed them. And as ſoon as they were delivered, they looked upon themſelves only as more at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to commit all thoſe abominations, for which they were carried into Captivity. Which ſtrange impenitency under Gods judgments does uſually manifeſt itſelf in theſe two Caſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When men have hardned themſelves in evil by a long practice, and cuſtom of ſinning. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom we ſay, is a ſecond Nature, and uſually gaineth ſuch ſtrength by time, that it grows more firm than either Nature or Religion. It hardens the Heart, ſears the Conſcience, makes the man uncapable of the impreſſions of ſorrow, and as ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55156:15"/>unable to Repent, as the Aethiopian <hi>to change his skin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. xiii. 23.</note> 
               <hi>or the Leopard to be freed from his ſpots.</hi> The judgments of God may raze the skin, but cannot pierce ſo deep as to would the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>It is ſeen ſomtimes in Apoplectick Diſtempers, that they ſo far ſtupifie the Patients, that no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities can reduce them to acts of life, and it is ſaid that they have afterwards grown ſenſible, when they have been laid out, and covered in their Graves, and revived amidſt the flames of their Funeral Pile. In the ſame ſenſeleſs condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion does a Cuſtom of ſin place the obdurate ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the auſtereſt of the Divine methods, the Sword, Peſtilence, and Famine, and all the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſymptoms of impendent wrath, ſhall in no wiſe prevail with him to call his ſins to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, or to raiſe him from his drowſineſs and ſtupidity; ſo that he never awakes, till he finds the flames of Hell about his ears, nor recovers the ſenſe of his ſins, till it ſerves to no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but to increaſe the reſentments of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            <p>The judgments of God quite loſe their end up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a man. He cries perhaps, and roars un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his torments, but he has no apprehenſions of Gods deſign in inflicting them. Like thoſe of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> vii. 14. <hi>They have not cryed unto me with their hearts when they howled upon their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55156:16"/>beds.</hi> He has felt the pain and anguiſh in the fleſh, but has no ſenſe at all of any impreſſions upon the Spirit. Like a man in a melancholic, and a troubleſom dream, he is ſcared perhaps and frighted with the terrors of the Almighty, but as ſoon as the noiſe is over, he quickly returns to his former ſlumber, and ſecurity.</p>
            <p>This is ordinarily the ſtate of the habitual ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, placed beyond the poſſibility of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by the Divine corrections, unleſs God together with his judgments ſet in with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful aſſiſtances of his Grace, and Spirit, which that man certainly has little reaſon to expect, who hath ſo long grieved, reſiſted and ſtood out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>And this conſideration ſuggeſts a ſecond Caſe, in which the judgments of God uſually prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual to Repentance, when men have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in their ſins under the plentiful diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Grace and Mercy. Abuſed mercies are the great aggravations of the iniquities of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And this we may be ſure of, that whatever tends to <hi>fill up the meaſure</hi> of our ſins, increaſes likewiſe the difficulty of our Repentance. When <hi>the goodneſs of God will not lead men to Repentance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. ii. 4, 5.</note> when they <hi>deſpiſe the riches of his forbearance, and long ſuffering,</hi> their hearts then grow <hi>hardned, and impenitent, they treaſure up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:55156:16"/>
            <p>And indeed how can it be expected, that thou ſhouldft comply with this method of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, who haſt already rejected and refuſed ſo many? If the Sword of Gods Judgments had not yet overtaken thee, yet he has been long fighting againſt thee with the <hi>ſword of his mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. ii. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> with the tenders of his Goſpel and the effers of his Grace. He has been long inviting, importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and purſuing thee, with the Preaching of his Word, the ſuggeſtions of his Spirit, the blood of his Son, the joys of Heaven, and the torments of Hell, thy own vows, engagements, and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions. And how can we then think that the ſhowers of Gods judgments ſhould prove more prevalent than the ſunſhine of his mercies, and out-weigh the united force of all theſe great inducements to move us unto Repentance?</p>
            <p>We have an inſtance, that ſpeaks home to this, <hi>Luke</hi> xvi. where the Rich man for his impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and neglecting his day of Grace, being tormented in the flames of Hell, deſires <hi>Father Abraham</hi> to ſend <hi>Lazarus</hi> to his five brethren, that ſurvived him, to forewarn them of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of their ſins, and what bitterneſs there is in the end of tranſgreſſion, leſt they ſhould alſo come <hi>into the ſame place of torment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke xvi. 28.</note> But <hi>Abraham</hi> tells him <hi>they have</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> who have clearly revealed their duty, and their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon the neglect of it, <hi>let them hear them.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:55156:17"/>Nay Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>But if one went from the dead, they will repent.</hi> And would not any one think, that ſuch a meſſage as this were very like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to produce Repentance? For one coming from the dead would be a viſible demonſtration of the ſouls exiſtence after its departure. And <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zus</hi> could decipher the joys of Heaven, and give a true account of the ſufferings of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as being a perſon who had a ſight of theſe, a taſt and experience of the other. And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all theſe high probabilities, of the efficacy of this method, Father <hi>Abraham</hi> concludes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> 
               <hi>If they hear not</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets, neither will they be perſuaded by one coming from the dead.</hi> From which we may infer, applying this parable to our preſent purpoſe, that thoſe who are not melted by the offers of his Grace, will be the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hardned by the terrors of his Judgments, and that ſuch as have rejected thoſe former Mercies, if they will not be perſuaded by one coming from the dead, they will ſurely not Repent, though they themſelves are going to them.</p>
            <p>Theſe are two Caſes in which the impenitency of a people under Gods Judgments uſually hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens. I proceed now to ſome more particular Cauſes of it, which is the next point to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And the firſt cauſe is a ſpirit of Atheiſm and Infidelity, which has poſſeſt the minds of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55156:17"/>men, which takes their eyes off from God, and fixes them upon ſecond and inferior cauſes. The Plague is nothing elſe but ſome infectious atoms in the air, which in certain determinate periods of time gather together for the annoyance of a City or a Nation. Wars are cauſed meerly by the different intereſts of States, which engage them in mutual provocations of one another, and by that means diſpoſe Princes to Choler and Revenge. The Revolutions of Government proceed from the ambition and treachery of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who, whenever they find an opportunity, will be ready to break forth to diſengage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their ſubjection, and involve a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Kindom in blood, ruine, and confuſion. It was <hi>Jorams</hi> deſperate reſolution in the Siege of Samaria, <hi>This evil is of the Lord, wherefore ſhould I wait upon the Lord any longer?</hi> But the men whom we now ſpeak of conclude with a little better Logick, but as bad Divinity, Theſe evils are not from the Lord, therefore why ſhould we wait upon him? It is not <hi>he that has broken us,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it <hi>he, that muſt bind us up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was an error in the Heathens (which their own reaſon might have corrected) that they aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all their ordinary ſucceſs, or misfortune to themſelves, or their enemies, but any great, and extraordinary calamities either to <hi>fate</hi> or <hi>chance.</hi> And this engaged them in a great deal of perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55156:18"/>ſo that they knew not which way to turn themſelves, when difficulties preſſed upon them. But methinks thoſe that live in a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Nation and call themſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſhould be better taught, who are inſtructed by the Sacred Oracles to impute all the miſeries that befal them to an over-ruling Cauſe, to diſcover the <hi>Finger of God</hi> in the hand of an enemy, and aſcribe all events whatſoever (even ſuch as are brought upon them by the inſtrumental mediation of ſecondary Agents) to the Juſtice, Wildom and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, the Supreme Governour of the World.</p>
            <p>It is the Lord,<note place="margin">2 Sam, xvi. 31.</note> that bids <hi>Shimei to curſe David,</hi> and that raiſes up to him <hi>enemies out of his own houſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">xxi. II. 1 Kings xii. 15.</note> If King <hi>Rehoboam</hi> will not hearken to Faithful Counſel, the <hi>Cauſe is from the Lord.</hi> And through the <hi>anger of the Lord</hi> it came to paſs,<note place="margin">2 Kings xxiv. 20.</note> that <hi>Zedekiah</hi> Rebelled againſt the King of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when <hi>Babylon</hi> has filled up the meaſure of her iniquities, it is <hi>the Lord</hi> that raiſes up <hi>Cyrus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. xlv. 4.</note> that <hi>calls him by his name,</hi> that marches forth with his Armies to bring upon her, a ſwift, ſudden, and ſurprizing deſolation. <hi>Can a bird</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Amos) fall in a ſuare upon the earth where no gin is laid for him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos iii. 5.</note> 
               <hi>And ſhall there be any evil in the City which the Lord hath not done?</hi> It is God, and not the Air, the Elements, or the Stars, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55156:18"/>brings the Famine or Peſtilence upon a Nation. It is God, and not man, whether he be the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Enemy, or the Domeſtick Rebel that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns a State, and diſſolves a Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Theſe inſtances are ſufficient to evince the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine efficiency in the works of ſecond Cauſes. And if the infidel notwithſtanding will not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the Doctrine of a Providence, we muſt even leave him to be convinced (as he certainly will either in this life or in another) by Gods own immediate ſtroke. This in the mean time is certain, that this prodigious humour of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, Scepticiſm, and Infidelity, which ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds in this Nation, is both a real cauſe of mens impenitency under Judgments, and a dreadful ſymptom, that God will go on to judg and afflict them ſtill. And by this means (I great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fear) our adverſaries of <hi>Rome</hi> are more likely to compaſs their ends upon us than by any of their other artifices, and ſtratagems whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p n="2">II. There is a great indifferency upon the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tits of men, as to the truth or honeſty of the Cauſe that they are engaged in. Which makes them inſtead of thinking of the proper expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents to ſave their Country from ruine, to plot and contrive how they may advance themſelves in the next turn of affairs, and the revolution of the Government.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:55156:19"/>
            <p>Men that have been uſed to fiſh in troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and by little tricks and devices of their own to wind themſelves in with that ſide that gets up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt, will never in any National calamity entertain any thoughts of returning unto God, as long as they can have recourſe to the ſame arts to ſave and ſecure themſelves.</p>
            <p>And this ſeems to be the Caſe of <hi>Ephraim</hi> in the Text. He ſtood in no great fear of the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> becauſe he had no concern for his God, and was not at all ſenſible of his miſery in being carried away Captive into a Land of Idols, as long as he was already prepared to worſhip after <hi>the manner of the gods of the Land.</hi> Thus we find the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were in the time of <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings xviii. 21.</note> when they <hi>halted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, two opinions</hi> between <hi>God and Baal.</hi> Such were thoſe Nations whom the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> placed in the Cities of <hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">xvii. 33.</note> 
               <hi>that feared the Lord and ſerved Idols.</hi> And the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zephany</hi> who could <hi>ſwear by God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeph i. 5.</note> 
               <hi>and ſwear by</hi> Melchom. Such as theſe are men ready and prepared for a change, whatever it be, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved if the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> (or whoever elſe) get the upper hand, that Idolatry and Superſtition ſhall put no ſtop to their preferment. Men that can counterfeit any Religion are really of none at all. And therefore whatever pretences they may make for the preſent, what is there that can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them (when occaſion ſerves) from making
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55156:19"/>the beſt advantages they can for themſelves, by coupling in with that ſide, that wins the day.</p>
            <p>But however ſuch as theſe by their arts and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes may make a ſhift for a while, yet <hi>God will not be mocked.</hi> The time will certainly come, when <hi>the ſinners in</hi> Sion <hi>ſhall be afraid, when fear ſhall ſurpriſe the Hypocrites.</hi> And perhaps it may be no leſſening of their miſeries, that they are the men to be deſtroyed laſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> in the Primitive Church, were a ſort of Hereticks, who profeſt the name of Chriſtians, and yet held it lawful to Apoſtatize in time of danger, and comply with the <hi>Jews</hi> for fear of Perſecution. But when the days of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and viſitation came, God makes a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between thoſe Carnal pretenders, and ſuch as continued ſtedfaſt to the profeſſion of his Truth. He provides a <hi>Pella</hi> for the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> a hiding place for them to retire to in that <hi>day of the Lords anger,</hi> but leaves thoſe abominable Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to be deſtroyed with the Crucifiers of Chriſt, and <hi>Hypocrites</hi> to periſh with <hi>Unbelievers.</hi> And this is ſaid by ſome to be the accompliſhment of that prediction of our Saviour, <hi>He that will ſave his life ſhall loſe it,</hi> when the <hi>Gnoſtics</hi> who by their compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances expected ſhelter among <hi>the Jews</hi> were toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>them</hi> ſo <hi>ſignally</hi> involved in the ſame ruin.</p>
            <p>Remember (I beſeech you) what the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> got by this double dealing with their God, by all
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55156:20"/>their Politick Confederacies with <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and at laſt determine what you will ſtand to (whatever comes on't) Reſolve with <hi>Mattathias</hi> in the Book of <hi>Macchabees.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Mac. ii. 22.</note> 
               <hi>God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid we ſhould forſake the Law and the Ordinances; We will not hearken to go from our Religion either on the right hand or on the leſt.</hi> I ſpeak to wiſe men, <hi>Judg ye what I ſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. There are a third ſort of men among us, who though they acknowledg God to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of our calamities, and imquity to deſerve them, yet hinder themſelves from true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance as much by a ſtiff Zeal for their ſeveral Parties, as others do by their lukewarmneſs and indifferency to them all. It was a ſtrangely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident preſumption in the <hi>Jews,</hi> that they thought themſelves wholly unconcerned in the event of Gods Judgments, and truſted in lying words, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Jer. vii. 4.</note> 
               <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are theſe.</hi> The ſame <hi>Jewiſh</hi> conceits at this day does a fond <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the hearts of men: Which inclines them only to cenſure others as the cauſes of our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, how loud ſoever Gods Judgments call upon them to accuſe, and condemn themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Fanaticks impute our ſufferings to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration of the King, the reſettlement of the <hi>Church,</hi> and to the throwing down of the Godly party from their unjuſt and arbitrary Dominion.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55156:20"/>And this makes them look upon all publick di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, as deſigned on purpoſe to make way for them to return to their beloved Tyranny and Uſurpation. And have not others better grounds to reply that God is now making inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for blood, and that the murder of our late Soveraign is required, and viſited upon this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Generation?</p>
            <p>The Diſſenter makes loud out-cries againſt us, that there is ſo much Will-worſhip and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion practiſed in our Church, that Popery when it comes, is very likely to meet with a ready enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment without any conſiderable oppoſition. And have not we far juſter reaſon to recriminate upon them, that their uncharitable Diviſions keeping up the intereſts of their ſeveral parties, their refuſal of compliance in ſuch things as by their own acknowledgment they may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſubmit to, and making offences of things indifferent, which the word of God has never declared to be ſo, have ſo far weakned the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Intereſt, as to give incouragement to the Papiſts in their preſent attempts againſt us, and our Religion?</p>
            <p>But ſurely (which ſide ſoever be in the right) this is not the true method to ſecure us from our fears, or to prevent our dangers. Let us aſſure ourſelves, that no conceited priviledges will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect us in our ſins from the wrath of God. <hi>You
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55156:21"/>only have I known</hi> (ſays God) <hi>of all the Families of the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos iii. 2.</note> It does not follow, and therefore you will I ſpare, but <hi>therefore you will I puniſh for your iniquities.</hi> In the mean time this bold, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious charging of others is the ready way to draw down Gods Judgments upon us both. And if we would all agree to be ſevere in judging of ourſelves, we ſhould be a great deal nearer to Peace and Union with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome cauſes of our obſtinacy under Gods Judgments. It remains that I ſpeak a word or two concerning the greatneſs of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation together with ſome brief Application to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And indeed what can poſſibly be imagined of a more daring and provoking Nature than this? What can a people do more to incenſe the God of Heaven, and cauſe his anger to ſmoak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch a ſtubborn Generation? It directly flies in the face of the Divine Majeſty, and caſts an intolerable ſlur upon all his excellent perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. It tramples upon his Juſtice, croſſes and thwarts the deſigns of his Mercy. It baffles his Goodneſs, and defeats the ends of his moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable Wiſdom. It affronts his abſolute and uncontrollable Dominion, as if he wanted Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſufficient to vindicate the reputation of his Laws. It defies and braves his Power, as if
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55156:21"/>man were able to contend with his Maker, as if Omnipotence had done its worſt, were quite ſpent, and had no other Judgments in ſtore to vex and conſume a ſinful people.</p>
            <p>This is certainly the true intent and meaning of every obſtinate ſinners language, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues incorrigible under the Divine Judgments. And then what can be expected, but, ſince men thus rob God of his Honor by their impenitence, that he ſhould at laſt aſſert, and vindicate it by the juſt retaliation of wrath and vengeance? He will infallibly <hi>get honor upon</hi> Pharaoh <hi>and all his hoſt,</hi> and make a people that have defamed him to be a <hi>by-word and reproach among the Nations.</hi> It is ſaid of King Ahaz, <hi>that in the time of his diſtreſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chronicl. xxviii. 22.</note> 
               <hi>he treſpaſſed yet more.</hi> But God ſets a mark upon him: <hi>This is that King</hi> Ahaz. He points him out with a ſpecial brand of reproach and ignominy for an example, and warning to all future Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>We read, <hi>Jer.</hi> v. 3. <hi>O Lord, are not thine eyes upon the truth? thou haſt ſmitten, but they have not giveved; thou haſt conſumed them, but they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to receive correction; they have made their faces harder than a rock, they have refuſed to return.</hi> And then God proceeds to denounce further Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, till it follows, v. 7. <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this?</hi> There is certainly a deſperate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity in that guilt, at which Divine Wiſdom
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55156:22"/>ſeems at a ſtand; which has (as it were) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted the riches of his Goodneſs, non-plult and poſed him, who is infinite in Mercy, to contrive and find out a pardon.</p>
            <p>And how terrible the wrath of the Lord is, when it is once kindled againſt an impenitent and obdurate Nation, we have a lively inſtance in his proceedings with the <hi>Jews,</hi> when he could bear with them no longer, when he quite cut them off from being a people, when they had fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up the meaſure of their Fathers, and when God viſited upon them, together with the blood of Chriſt, all the innocent blood that had been ſpilt, <hi>from the blood of righteous</hi> Abel <hi>to the blood of</hi> Zacharias <hi>the ſon of</hi> Barachias, <hi>who was ſlain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Temple and Altar.</hi> A viſitation ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and aſtoniſhing, as if God deſigned in their deſtruction to ſhew an experiment what an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Arm was able to do, what deſolations he could bring upon a Land for the wickedneſs of thoſe that dwell therein.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>in</hi> Jury <hi>God was known, and his name was great in</hi> Iſrael; though <hi>of the Temple at</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>God had ſaid, that he would put his name there, and that his eyes and his heart ſhould be there perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually;</hi> yet he now wonderfully declares to the whole world, that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is no longer the place of his reſt, that he has forſook his Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool, abhorred his Sanctuary, and caſt off his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55156:22"/>Altar. If I had now time to purſue all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal circumſtances of that dreadful ſtory, what incredible numbers moſt miſerably periſht by the Peſtilence, and the Famine, how many were deſtroyed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Armies, and (which was yet more tragical, and frightful) how many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the executioners of Gods vengeance upon themſelves, and how viſibly the hand of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in all; we ſhould quickly conclude it to be the moſt fearful calamity, that was ever exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted upon a people on this ſide Hell, ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the day of Judgment can give us a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the horror of it. Upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion we may fitly uſe the words of the Prophet Daniel, <hi>Under the whole heavens has not been done,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. ix. 12.</note> 
               <hi>as has been done upon</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p>I have no deſign to make any Application of this fearful ſtory to our ſelves. We have not yet had the voice in the Temple, the terrible Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, or the flaming Sword, and from theſe late diſcoveries that have been made amongſt us, we have ſome reaſon to hope that our deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is not ſo near. But though we have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to forebode deſtruction, yet we have loud Alarms to provide againſt it. And if our impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence under Gods Judgments continue at the ſame rate with theirs, what can we otherwiſe expect, but that we ſhall alſo periſh in the like dreadful deſolation?</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:55156:23"/>
            <p>I cannot here pretend to deſcribe the ſucceſſive advances of afflicting Providences, which God Almighty hath ſent upon this unfortunate Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. How fatal were the miſeries of the Civil-war! How ſad and diſmal the confuſions, that ſucceeded it! We heard nothing among us but the cries of the oppreſſed, the confuſed <hi>noiſe of the Battel, of the warrier, and garments rould in blood.</hi> But after we had been long exerciſed with this ſevere diſcipline, God at length turns our Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, brings back our Royal Sovereign to ſit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Throne of his Fathers, and eſtabliſhes the whole Nation in a full poſſeſſion of their Rights, and Laws, their Liberties, and Religion. And (which ought the more to endear our deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) all this was brought about by a Miracle of Mercy far beyond all our hopes and contrivances, at a time, when we were quite loſt, without all viſible means of a Reſtoration.</p>
            <p>And now what ought have been the Natural reſult of this? What language could have been more ſuitable for a redeemed people, than thoſe words of Ezra,<note place="margin">Ezra ix. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>Seeing thou haſt puniſht us leſs than our iniquities have deſerved, and haſt given us ſuch a deliverance as this, ſhall we again break thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi> But lo! thus has it come to paſs, by a prodigy of Ingratitude more aſtoniſhing than the Mercy, that we have again provoked the Lord to take the Sword into his Hand, to Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55156:23"/>his deſtroying Angel to bring the Peſtilence into our Streets, to ſend upon us a raging and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Fire, which laid waſt the Metropolis of the Kingdom. Together with theſe Calamities, he raiſes up againſt us a Foreign Enemy to make war upon our Coaſts, <hi>to ſcoff at Kings, and make Princes a ſcorn unto them,</hi> to break our chains, <hi>deride our ſtrong holds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. i. 10.</note> and <hi>gather our captivity as the ſands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ever ſince that time, we have continued under the ſad apprehenſions of more fearful Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments than theſe. There has remained upon the Nation great <hi>diſtreſs and perplexity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke xxi, 25.</note> 
               <hi>mens hearts failing them for fear, and for looking after thoſe things that are coming upon the earth.</hi> We have long ſtood in fear of a Famine of the Word, of the removal of the Candleſtick, of the glory of God in his Church ready to depart from us. To be plain, and in a word, we are threatned with the return of <hi>Popery</hi> upon the Kingdom, that is, to have the practice of the groſſeſt Impiety, Superſtition, and dolatry introduced among us, and all the ſincere profeſſors of the Truth of the Goſpel in every corner of the Land Maſſacred, Burnt, Rackt and Tormented, becauſe they will not receive the <hi>mark of the beaſt in their forehead,</hi> nor comply with theſe abominations.</p>
            <p>This is the Sword which the Lord ſeems to hang over us this day. And is there any way left to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55156:24"/>prevent, or ſtop it from the intended execution? If inſtead of our gratitude to God for ſuch ſignal mercies, as he has reacht forth unto us, we begin to fret and murmur at our enjoyments, and are ready to make us a <hi>Captain to return into</hi> Aegypt, is it not Juſt with God to cauſe <hi>Aegypt</hi> to return to us, and enſlave both King and People to the mercileſs Uſurpation of a Foreign Power? If after we have ſo long lived under a Faithful Preaching of the Word, a ſincere Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, a liberal proviſion of all the means of Grace, we have loathed our <hi>Manna</hi> and deſpiſed our Mercies, if we have either quite withdrawn from the Publick Aſſemblies, or not brought forth fruit in any wiſe anſwerable to thoſe great advantages, which we have, of being ſaved; may we not reaſonably preſume, that we have ſo far provoked the Lord, as to give us up to a people, who will deprive us of theſe bleſſings, who with the cruelty of <hi>Diocleſian</hi> will kindle a Fire either for our Bibles, or our Selves, who inſtead of the word of God will obtrude upon us their own inventions, rob us of one half of the bleſſed Sacrament, and ſet up the Idol of the Maſs inſtead of the other?<note place="margin">2 Theſ. ii. 10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>If we have not received the love of the truth that we might be ſaved:</hi> Is it not greatly to be feared <hi>that for this cauſe God will ſend us ſtrong deluſions, that we ſhall believe lies; that all may be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned who believe not the truth, but have pleaſure in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:55156:24"/>
            <p>If after all thoſe mixtures and viciſſitudes of Providence that we have had (as <hi>Salvian</hi> ſays of the Spaniards, <hi>Mutata ſors ſed non mutata vitioſitas</hi>) there remains ſtill the ſame ſenſleſneſs under Gods Judgments, the ſame unthankfulneſs for his Mercies, the ſame Atheiſm, Prophaneneſs and Infidelity, from which God by all this variety of his methods has indeavoured to reclaim us: If the Nation is full of Whoredoms, and <hi>becauſe of ſwearing the Land mourneth:</hi> If Treaſon dares ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with an open Face, and ſpread dayly Libels, and Defamations againſt the Government: If Schiſms and Factions thrive and proſper, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain threaten the beſt of Churches in the world: ſurely God will viſit for theſe things, his ſoul will yet further <hi>be avenged upon ſuch a Nation as this.</hi> May we not juſtly fear that God will raiſe up againſt us a bitter, <hi>and haſty Nation to land upon our Coaſts, to march through the breadth of the Land, and poſſeſs the dwelling places that are not theirs;</hi> that he will henceforth forget to be gracious, and ſhut up his loving kindneſs in an utter diſpleaſure, that he will bring upon us that heavy doom which our Saviour of old denounced to his own people, <hi>Therefore I ſay unto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. xxi. 43.</note> 
               <hi>that the Kingdom of God ſhall be taken from you, and given to a Nation bringing forth the fruits of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know but one way left to prevent the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of theſe dreadful Judgments, which is,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55156:25"/>ſeriouſly to put in practice that great duty which we are called to this day, <hi>to repent and turn from our tranſgreſsions, that ſo iniquity may not be our ruine.</hi> This is the only courſe left us to reſcue us from our preſent miſeries, and preſerve us from the evil, which is otherwiſe certainly to come upon us. And how great ſoever our fears are, we have yet ſome comfortable grounds to hope, that our day of Grace is not yet paſt, the door is not ſhut againſt us, but that we are ſtill within the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities of Repentance. It ſeems that we are not yet quite caſt off, by that wonderful diſcovery which God hath made amongſt us of a Helliſh Plot for the Aſſaſſinating of our King, and the Subverſion of our Government and Religion. And therefore though we might be apt to conclude with <hi>Manoah</hi> in the Book of <hi>Judges. We ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly die, becauſe we have ſeen God,</hi> ſo terrible in his Judgments in the midſt of us? Yet we may now with <hi>Manoahs</hi> wife make a better and more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable inference:<note place="margin">Judg. xiii. 12, 23.</note> 
               <hi>If the Lord were pleaſed to kill us, he would not have ſhewed us all theſe things, nor would he (as at this time) have told us ſuch things as theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us be careful therefore to improve this ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Providence to thoſe ſerious purpoſes, for which God intends it, which are to break off our ſins by Repentance, to reform and amend our lives: Leſt by continuing in our tranſgreſſions,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55156:25"/>we defeat the deſigns of his goodneſs, and hinder him from going on to compleat our deliverance: Leſt this great Mercy prove but a lightning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore death, and notwithſtanding this, <hi>if we ſtill do wickedly, we be conſumed, both we, and our King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that (we ſee) a way ſtill lies open for us to appeaſe the wrath of God and procure his favor; which if we all ſincerely reſolve to walk in, he will ſhine upon your Counſels, bleſs your En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes, and proſper your Undertakings; he will be a wall of fire round about us, when he is thus the glory in the midſt of us, he will heal our back-ſlidings and make up our breaches, he will defeat the deſigns of the enemies of our Peace, <hi>and he will remember the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
